okay hello everyone
it's October 7th 2022 we're in the sixth
meeting for the second cohort
of the textbook group
today we're going to be discussing
chapter three for the first time
so we have a few
questions to explore on three but before
we do
would anyone like to just
say hello or give any
overview thoughts on chapter three
before we go into more specific
questions
you can raise your hand or just unmute
and just go for it
I'll wait for someone to make a comment
on chapter three
yep
to active inference with the
principle of least action and the
introduction of
of Markov blankets
okay how does that differ from previous
approaches or relative to what
but
I guess instead of instead of starting
with
um
instead of starting with the notion that
you have
some agent
that's creating a representation of its
world
you
um
you start with like in
axiomatic view from physics
that
when applied to
um
to biological entities
GIF leads to the at least the same same
conclusion
as chapter two
all right awesome thank you
anyone can raise their hand or just go
for it General thoughts on chapter three
and or
what is the high road to active
inference
foreign
having read chapters 2 and 3.
how does anybody want to remark on
figure 1.2
okay I I'll I'll make a short remark
to me this this figure
um
I guess these uh elements like surprise
minimization Mark of blanket looks like
they are they are inserted in the
pictures like sequentially but it
doesn't seem to me that they actually
represent a sequence for understanding
the
the the approach they're just various
aspects of uh of either the the physics
approach or
in the lower part of the figure of the
Bayesian approach
if I if I understood it correctly
because at first I thought it was like a
path you know starting from the free
energy principle and then first to
self-organization then surprise
minimization Mark of blanket predictive
processing and I don't know if it's
if it is actually a progression
of Concepts or actually I don't know
what do you think
yeah it's a great
question anyone can give a thought
what do the ordering of the terms mean
are these train stops along the way blue
or child
so I just wanted to say that um the live
stream where Maria really gave a lot of
background on predictive processing
predictive coding like the difference
between these two might be super helpful
um with regard to like a progression or
just evaluating that lineage in more
detail
um yeah sure I'll add link there
um one option would be that these are
historical like this is this chronology
of ideas another one would be that
they're pedagogical that this is a
learning path another might be uh formal
or technical
like one of them are one of the
directions are dependencies
or required but not necessarily the most
pedagogical path Ali
[Music]
um
yeah I also think that the organization
of this uh particular figure is more
like the branch
because of a tree and then uh something
uh sequential so they might not
represent any uh specific preference to
go through all of these steps in order
to achieve a particular goal where just
try it just tries to lump together
relevant Concepts in two different
branches so that's why I see it at least
foreign
yes the tree
um fep tree
from uh 2010
with a lot of the early sort of
directions and pointers towards areas of
synthesis
um
anyone else want to just add any other
thoughts like what is the high road
or how did they feel about chapter three
overall
foreign
Technical and specific questions to dive
into but it's really important to
understand chapter two and the low road
and chapter 3 being the high road and
the way that they're distinguished
in terms of the low road
beginning from a
framework for doing statistics learning
updating and so on
but not necessarily an imperative for
survival
in contrast in the high road
the beginning
[Music]
stance
is around the imperative for survival
which is kind of a biological way to
frame it or the slightly even more
deflationary imperative for repeated
measurements
which is more of a Quantum or a physics
way to be framing the issue in terms of
stochastic processes and measurement
Theory
where if something cannot be measuring
itself it's not going to see itself
around for long and if something is not
a thing to something else it's not being
measured over a given time scale within
a given variance Criterion it also is
going to be quote not a thing so this
imperative for
uh persistence
and finding manifolds of stability or
bounded spaces
is an imperative that isn't
intrinsically within Bayesian theorem
but active inference is being situated
at the intersection of the Bayesian
methods and the imperative for
persistence and or recur or repeated
measurements Ali
uh yes one of the I think the most
probably the most Central concept of
chapter three
uh on which all the other material seems
to
um seems to evolve is the concept of
Mark of blanket but
but in this particular chapter I think
the marker blanket I mean the nature of
markup blanket has not made uh quite
explicit so I just wanted to emphasize a
critical point about this whole concept
which has caused a lot of lots of
confusions and misunderstandings around
it and
namely uh some people think markup
blanket is actually some a kind
of spatial temporal boundary around the
system
but as the paper and Bayesian mechanics
makes clear uh marker blanket is
actually a boundary
a boundary on state space and it doesn't
necessarily or it doesn't always
translate into any spatial temporal
boundary in some cases uh
first
for example in the cells or organelles
or things like that we can see the
spatial temporal manifestation of markup
blanket but that's not always the case
so yeah that's one of the points I think
is crucial to understanding this whole
um
High Road approach to active inference
hmm
thank you Ali very interesting points
so they do
in the first box of the chapter and in
the first non-introduction section
discuss Marco blankets so it's
definitely something that we want to um
follow on
so let's
we're
done for now with the just general
discussion around what the high road is
um good yes Giuseppe please
okay no it's just on this topic that
it's true that the mark of blanket is is
explained
they quite clearly if if succinctly in
that part but
then I don't think it throughout the
book is actually
uh is actually
used
or describe the in details from the
computational point of view
that I
mean I think it's it's
it's described it's it's defined there
but then I to me since that doesn't
appear much in the in the more
computational later parts of the book
that that was my impression
so
the concept is quite clear
uh but
I'm not sure how it um it applies then
practically just just laying out the
model probably in laying out the
specifics of the model that that defines
by itself the the the relevant Mark of
blanket probably
thank you
um Ali
[Music]
uh yes uh one reason for that might be
at least according to my personal
communication with Maxwell ramstead uh
you see uh the problem of identifying
markup blankets from data uh is still an
outstanding uh issue and problem uh
among fep researchers uh on which versus
lab is actively working on so that's not
a resolved problem I guess uh yet so
that's I think one of the reasons they
have not alluded to the concept of
Market blankets
so much throughout the whole through the
throughout the rest of the book uh the
other reason is uh the recent literature
somehow tries to uh
reduce its dependence on this whole
concept of markup blanket
um because of various reasons
so yeah these two reasons might be
sufficient to explain its lack of
appearance or at least explicit
appearance
in much of the book
Thank you
great yeah I think um this this question
will help us dive further into this
question
on page 43
they uh are writing so first off anyone
who wanted to describe on a more
technical note we can bring it up later
or sooner what a Markov blanket is
because it is one of the core
um
terms in brief a markup blanket is the
set of variables that mediate all
statistical interactions between a
system and environments and those
parentheses cover a lot that is not the
same thing as the actual mechanical or
material interactions between the system
and the environments that is the map
territory fallacy or failure to
distinguish although one can't also
swing too far into the map territory
fallacy fallacy area which we've talked
about earlier
um
this
the markout blanket and what it does
is a restatement of the classical action
perception cycle
where an Adaptive system and its
environment can interact only through
actions and observations respectively
so how's the Marco blanket a restatement
of the classical action perception cycle
I feel that this is an important
question to understand to contextualize
active inference Within
the history of models like cybernetics
control theory ecological psychology
and qualitative and quantitative models
of perception and action
kind of goes without saying but it's a
really important note
and we see multiple representations of
the action perception Loop
so figure three one
shows the auction perception Loop
along with the particular partition
that's the one that's separated into
internal and external States along with
the blanket States
which makes internal and external
conditionally independent
and then the blanket states are further
decomposed into active States those with
outgoing dependencies from the
perspective of internal States and
sensory States those with internal
dependencies
although note some asterisks in the
interpretation for example around which
arrows have two directions and which
ones don't
so here's figure 3.1
the Markov blanket it's Dynamic it's
changing in time the states are changing
in time
separating partitioning
internal States hear the brain from the
environments
and all of the functions
are described in terms of rates of
change x u y and mu
and the dot over the top is like the
derivative so they're all being solved
for in terms of how they change their
time
and they're all being described with
these F functions that are themselves
comprised of a deterministic
component
that's the um average rate of change
over these arguments coming into the
deterministic components of the equation
and
Omega which is some sort of random
fluctuation parameter
so it's kind of like a signal to noise
partitioning
statistical variance
Within
the change characteristics
of a given state
corresponding to particular partitioned
variables
but we've also seen other
representations of the action perception
Loop
so here's one of the simpler ones from
figure one this is the first figure in
the book
and we can think about how like the
active States even though they're coming
up
from the right here and they're coming
kind of down from the left here
in both situations it's like this is the
engagement
between the agent and the niche
okay but then there are some other
representations too
like figure two two
here
we see a proto-blanket forming though
not described as such and without like
for example an arrow connecting
these two nodes between observation and
action
and more of an emphasis on the way that
hidden states are being either actually
generative of the observations that's
the generative process or that hidden
states of the generative model are doing
inference on the observations
so that's one other
um representation
and then there's this representation
where here action is coming out of
discrepancy
as is perception learning generative
model change
and we see observation coming into
discrepancy
so
what is the action perception cycle
and where do Markov blankets come into
play
in terms of even the classical ways of
thinking about control systems
if one looks up control Loop
they'll find all kinds of diagrams
from cybernetics and control theory
that can entirely be interpreted
within a sort of entity
getting input doing some sort of
processing and having outputs
so
how is the Marco blanket helping us
approach this Nexus of the entity in the
niche
well one thought or important piece to
note is that
some blanket States will exist
for any Bayesian graph that isn't fully
connected
anytime that you have a non-fully
connected base graph so not every node
is connected to every node
then there will be some other nodes
upon which
two other sets are a conditionally
independent
that's just what the nodes and edges
mean
in this kind of a graphical model
which is if nodes are random variables
and edges are statistical relationships
then nodes directly connected by an edge
have a direct statistical relationship
again not implying anything about the
material or the causal nature of the
world
so then
if two nodes do not have a statistical
relationship
they're either part of two different
graphs which can be seen as basically
partitions from each other
or they're going to be part of a
connected component of a graph
but there's some other nodes one or more
that intermediate such that those two
nodes of Interest
which are arbitrarily called internal
and external
have conditional independencies
that ends up simplifying and being
important for a lot of the computation
and it respects and reflects the sparse
coupling
of features in the world
so it's always just important to like
think back like where is something new
coming in
to active inference people have been
using partially observable Markov
decision processes
for many years for perception and
control issues before active inference
those models
also
are imbued with Markov blankets
just like any other
um
markovian setting in Time series
analysis or any sort of partially
observable model
so
just an important question for discourse
to continue on
how is the Marco blanket restating the
classical action perception cycle Ollie
yeah just as a side note I wanted to
point out again to um
I think an important error in this
particular figure
which I've included in the Errata so if
yeah and added a note there uh so if you
could please open
uh yeah for this yeah and open
the notes there I've added the
explanation for why
exactly yes thank you
so let's just put it
what Giuseppe no it makes sense the the
I think it's well spotted
yes there's many
changes and and um so again these are
like why it's so important for everybody
to make asynchronous contributions and
questions if they can
this is how we actually are going to
move the needle on the textbook making
sense and making impact
I know it's like an individual sense
making Journey as well
but also these kinds of questions like
what does this mean and the discourse
around them is gonna
catalyze the actual use of this area
like
um do you want to summarize what the
difference is between the existing
equations and the replacement
sure uh you see in the existing equation
in the book The marginal flow of sensory
states are expressed
uh in terms of blanket States namely U
and Y
and also the um the inter the
um I mean the external state but uh the
it should be the other way around I mean
the marginal flow sensory State should
be expressed only in terms of external
States and blanket States and the
marginal flow of active States should be
expressed in terms of
are only internal States and the blanket
States
thank you so yeah just to restate that
and also to build some intuition with
what these flows are and how they relate
so you and Y constitute B the blanket
States so sometimes you and Y are both
written
or B is written
to describe the blanket State variables
other times it might just be describing
a subset at which point not the whole
blank is being described just for
example the active States U or the
sensory States y are being described
then mu our internal States here and X
you know find x hidden States external
states with a note here that the
variables are different in different
presentations
so
um as it was written
we can read that this is the change in U
which is the active States is a function
of first a stochastic parameter about
you itself
but then the deterministic component
here is a function of the blanket States
and the hidden States
and conversely as written
why the change in observations Through
Time
is after accounting for a stochastic
term a flow function on blanket States
and internal States
whereas it's actually exactly the
opposite with X and mu being switched
between these two because actions should
reflect a flow over blanket and internal
States
sometimes called the particular States
because that's the particle that's
moving around that's the Bayesian
mechanical particle
and then observations should reflect a
flow on blanket States themselves
and hidden states of the world
foreign
and that's very related to this other
question so uh what does figure 3.1 mean
I think that's what we're looking at
how is it different than figure two five
and how is the agent's Niche
relationship describe qualitatively and
formally in active inference in other
areas so I think we kind of explored
that
um people can add any more notes but
this is like a really important level to
pull back to
whether it's somebody who's having a
question
or even uh well-intended or not
criticism of active inference or a
control theory
it can be useful are they describing
challenges of the world
like the map territory difference like
the complexity of the world always
transcending the structure and
complexity of our own models or
referring to the fundamental issues of
taking action amidst uncertainty
are people pointing to those issues and
then part of the community
describing the agent niche qualitatively
and or formally
or
are they sort of
suggesting or implying some kind of like
hidden other way of thinking about how
agents engage in the niche
because there's a lot of questions that
can arise
but these framings although here the
Markov blanket gives that kind of a
Bayesian statistical and graphical
um
uh stance on it and implementation
opportunity space which includes an
incredible number of computational
affordances like message passing
variational inference and so on
um
this
partitioning of the entity from the
niche figure from grounds
is not diverging from the traditions
of cybernetics and other areas
so just kind of like interesting are
people pointing to fundamental issues of
perception and action
which in some senses is our field
and are they
part of the building and the sense
making around those
scientific and meta-scientific models
or is it just a position of like well
it's not possible to model this
kind of random thought but
okay thank you
yes Ali
uh sorry just one other brief side note
about the term you used there the
particle particular States uh which you
mentioned is the joint set of the
blanket states and and the internal
State the other related term used in the
literature is the autonomous state which
refers to the Joint set of internal and
active States instead of the blanket
States we only take the internal active
States as the autonomous States or paths
that's just
thank you
this would kind of be a uh uh first and
ask phrasing that the idea that these
different
um sets are going to inherit from the
particular partition
so the first move is the base graph to
the particular partition
which is just this specific partition
between internal external States
mediated by a Markov blanket then
sometimes it's useful to talk about
specific
um sub sets of the particular partition
if we were only interested in one of
these categories we would just call it
by name like talking about just external
States or external State 11 dimension
11.
um but other times we want to talk about
partitioned States but still refer to
more than one type of state and so Ali
brought in this seconds clustering
the particular States that's the
particle that's moving around that's the
whole entity internal States and blanket
States and then also times it's
important to consider the action in the
internal States
because those are kind of the ones that
can be thought of as in a total control
situation they're the ones that are
under Direct Control
so like you can control your mind and
you can control your action
those are the autonomous States whereas
you can't directly influence sensory
States
but you might be able to take actions
that modify sensory states by changing
where you look or by changing some
aspect of the world
um so those are autonomous States and it
relates to this question can surprise
only be diminished through action
what does anyone think
foreign
here's the throwback to yes Ali first
yeah I just I wanted to point out to
exactly that uh the same place in the
text
which I as far as I know there are two
basic ways to uh reduce the surprisal or
minimize the surprise one of which is uh
through the action and the other one is
through updating the uh generative model
so
Yep this is the uh
changed beliefs
which is speaking more broadly than
personally held convictions
this is going to be pointing towards the
Continuum between perception learning
and deeper belief States in generative
models
so perception is changing beliefs
Bayesian beliefs which is to say
updating the generative model learning
and perception
on the other hand
there's action which can change the
world and so out of this discrepancy
it can be dissipated two ways it's kind
of like if there was like a Delta G A
Gibbs free energy
like something that was
um combustible
there's like a hill to go down
energetically and so now we're in an
informational space
but there's still at the um
Clash of predictions and observations
is a non-zero discrepancy
and from that discrepancy there can be
changes in the generative model
parameters
reflecting beliefs
and also
recourse to action
and active inference is about how
generative models which include beliefs
about action
resolve this kind of Nexus
through the flows on updating
oh sorry
um yeah what is the difference between
belief updating and mental action
all added as a question and then someone
can give a thought
any thoughts
well maybe mental action
um refers to the active States of
[Music]
um and nested more more nested Mark of
blanket so
it's
it's a
it's an action it's a modulation of
precision
on the
within the generative model and it's not
a motor action you know through motor
effectors
foreign
states that actually communicate with
the external world
but it's still internal
that's I don't know that's my take on it
may be wrong
yeah very uh nice I think just
more more discussions can be added so
just giving a quick thought belief
updating
could refer to any kind of parametric
updating at all it doesn't even have to
be like a cognitive model belief
updating is just any time that there's a
prior
that meets with an observation and gets
updated into a posterior
you have belief updating and we can use
Bayesian surprise to talk about belief
updating and so on
then as pointed out mental action as
it's used in the hierarchical models of
it
is referring to the policy selection
process that's hinted in the action
but the policy selection process or
module or archetype as oriented around
mental variables
so
it is almost out of necessity requiring
a nested or a hierarchical model
because there has to be like a sort of
base layer that is not mental action
but then at the second level or above
you can start to see the same kind of Pi
policy variables and the same way of
thinking about affordances and free
energy and expected free energy
minimization processes in the second
level or above
where those action like processes
or maybe even genuine action processes
are referring to cognitive States rather
than a motor effector as would be
understood as in the case of like
conventional motor action
whereas belief updating does not require
a hierarchical model it's just referring
very very broadly to Bayesian parametric
change
that makes sense thank you
all right so
um
can surprise be managed
um through action
no not only
like
you're surprised you know you expect it
to be 20 degrees
um and you're observing it's 25.
you can either engage in accent
selection to change the thermometer
under beliefs about how one's actions
change the world B Matrix
or one can just update
their model
two that is now what I expect
and of course that's the fun discussion
in active inference with expect and
prefer
because if organisms are in the game of
diminishing or bounding surprise
then there has to be this nuanced dance
between
what is being observed understanding it
to be simply the most likely
but you don't want to be on the likely
train off the cliff
so there has to also be a space for
slightly or very stubborn prior
preference distributions
that enable
increasingly intense policies
to be implemented
to actually shape the state of the world
and oneself back towards
that earlier expectation and preference
rather than engaging in just purely
cognitive updating
that's just speaking about it generally
but there's a lot to um
unpack
in a more um
model specific way
okay I'll leave share the link
oh awesome
awesome this looks like a good reference
and also uh live stream 25
I believe
was on mental action Sanford Smith
okay
let's
look towards this
question
does anyone want to just give an example
they can clarify synchrony between
internal and external States
what's the situation where we can think
of internal and external State
synchronizing
well I guess it depends on what we mean
by synchrony I mean synchrony like in uh
in on a fast time scale or
on a specific time scale
or
because the fact that the internal State
the reflect the the causal dynamics of
the environment
does not imply that they are immediately
synchronized right
yeah you're absolutely right the time
scale really matters and also it's
important to note that synchrony doesn't
mean lockstep it doesn't mean that
there's like a thermometer inside and a
thermometer outside and they're just
following each other
um synchrony can refer to the kind of
coordination that's more like
orchestrated
in the sense that if you had um two
people you know sawing a tree
they're both going to be taking opposite
actions
but there's still as high Mutual
information between those two action
policies
and they're able to be under General
synchrony
um so we can just think of a few areas
of examples
like one can always think of a computer
example because computers are clean
like you could just say well I have two
servers
and they're communicating on the time
or they're sending each other
information back and forth
or they're tracking some feature about
each other
you could imagine a communication
example
where there's some kind of semantic
coordination or synchrony
you could also imagine some kind of a
cellular or a physiological synchrony
like the inside of the cell is being
modeled as doing inference about insulin
levels outside of the cell and then the
insulin receptor is like the interface
and so there's synchronization
of cellular response to perceived or
inferred insulin concentration and the
external unobserved true circulating
insulin concentration mediated through
set States The Binding kinetics of
insulin on its receptors
like these are just kind of qualitative
examples but
there's a lot to
um drill down into more Ali
I think uh the word synchrony here uh
might have been used in the technical
term of uh the existence of a kind of
synchrony map between the two coupling
systems uh so in order for two systems
to be coupled there needs to be a
synchrony map uh namely Sigma between
them and uh the whole paper worked
example a paper by the alternate value
well provides uh multiple uh physical
examples for these kind of systems a
couple
systems and the most extreme case of
um those couple systems are the sparse
coupled systems in which the markup
blanket uh is the strongest or as they
call it the blanketedness or the blanket
index uh is basically zero but in some
other kinds of systems which in which
the internal and external states are
somehow more
closely follow each other the markup
blanket tends to
weaken and diminish so
yeah I think that's the meaning of the
word synchrony here
great Point
um
yep live stream 49.1 with Jacob and Ali
this week
it's recommended listen
and it's um
quite far-ranging so that is the most
state-of-the-art addressment of the
issue
a slightly older addressment of this
issue and also
um importantly coming back to what Ellie
mentioned about like the synchronization
manifold
so here's the uh example of bird song
that friston and friston and frith have
worked on
and uh this is some of the colorized
versions of the trace diagrams that are
seen in the textbook that are like a
little bit difficult to tell what's
happening when they're on colored lines
but just a
highlight the manifold there the x-axis
and the y-axis are the first and the
second Bird's belief States
and so
[Music]
um
to the extent that those
pairs of beliefs at a given moment exist
on the Y equals X line
they're believing the same thing at the
same time
whereas if you could imagine if they
were believing opposite things at the
same time you'd have like a negative
regression and if there was like
uncorrelated
or unsynchronized belief updating you'd
have just a scatter Cloud that wouldn't
have a significant regression slope
and so this diagram is showing how
before and after learning
the sharpness of the manifold
increases and a manifold is a lower
dimensional space within a higher
dimensional space so like we have a
two-dimensional space here with X and Y
and then
there's activity only on this manifold
which is being rejected effectively not
completely down into one dimension
because it's like a number line
or you can imagine it was a
three-dimensional space that was being
projected into a two-dimensional
manifold so manifold is just some lower
dimensional
structure in a higher dimensional phase
space
and so synchrony as Ali mentioned is
referring
um quite
particularly technically to
the um existence of synchronization
manifolds
and that is related to sparse coupling
blanket index all these topics all right
so in our last couple minutes we'll look
at this question about 3.4.1 and then
um over the coming week just
chill enjoy the week also add a few
other questions or discourse so that we
can come back to some of the latter
sections of chapter three
um next week so let's look at three four
one
in three four one
that's the section variational free
energy model evidence and surprise the
authors look at the equivalence between
variational free energy
model evidence and surprise and
formalize this relationship in equation
3.2 is it possible to unpack equation
3.2 to make these relationships easy to
understand
great question all right
so let's go to equation 3.2
here's what the equation looks like
then
our um
extremely helpful annotation
group
has gone through and provided this
natural language
unpacking so I'm just going to copy it
down and then we can look at what it
actually says
and then see how that relates to the the
question that was asked
which was about unpacking the
relationship
okay so the surprise
fracture I fancy I of the data y
conditioned vertical line on the model m
is equal to
the negative natural log Ln
of the conditional probability that's p
of the data y given m
with its upper bound being so this is a
less than or equal to sign so they could
be equal
these two the first and the second one
are equal
the second one and the third one could
be equal or
the third term could be larger
it's upper bound being the KL Divergence
dkl
between
two lines
the approximate posterior of hidden
States Q of X and the conditional
probability p
of hidden States X
conditioned vertical line on the data
and the model
minus
the natural log of the model evidence
P of the Y given the model
evidence for the data given the model
okay so the question was
what are the relationships between
variational free energy
that's the third term
model evidence the second term and
surprise the first term
the answer is not in the simple reading
of the equation but
that
gets us to
the discussion point
so how are these terms related the three
labeled terms on the bottom
a related question is why do we use
variational free energy
what is effective or useful about energy
measures at all
I'll give one thought and then one or
two other people could could add in
which is
um
we
don't want to be outside of our range of
surprise
and so by defining surprise in terms of
data
um and specifically within the natural
log space of data which has some just
nice properties
um
we want to stay bounded in the model
evidence if we want to have high or the
highest
or at least adequate model evidence
and that is equivalent to surprise we
can see the same y given m
now if we had that and had confidence
without a doubt in our model
and we knew how to calculate the
likelihood function of the data
then things would be easy and there are
situations where things are easy like
that
but there's other cases where we can
bound our surprisal which is to say
bound our model evidence
evidence lower bound the elbow elbow
and we can bound this intractable
quantity model evidence
with a divergence-based energy
calculation
and so we can do gradient descent
variational inference message passing
to block prints all these amazing things
on the variational free energy
and just know that at best we're going
to converge to the model evidence
so this is an optimization of an
optimizable quantity
of variational free energy
whereas model evidence is like if you
know it you know it but if you don't
you're kind of stuck
like How likely is this book
and it's super hard to understand how
changing one word would change the
overall likelihood distribution
and so that motivates approximate
heuristics for Bayesian inference
especially those that are authorized by
the sparsity of the data
and the variational free energy measure
allows us to bound surprise with
attractable Optima optimizable
function
rather than needing to for example
flesh out the total space of data
likelihoods and model likelihoods
which might be futile
I'm sure there are other better ways to
add things
so
so one thing that
[Music]
um
like after reading it uh
after reading about
[Music]
the after reading a book and after
reading other article it I kind of had
an Insight but I don't know if if it's
correct so that
the old energy stuff of course comes
from the physics and it's very
legitimate to be a bit
um a bit
a bit confused because this formulation
of uh with the Callback Library
Divergence is a purely statistical
um
quantity so I it's understandable that
somebody says what does energy have to
do with that
it seems to mean that
the two con the the the high high road
and the Lower Road converge here because
when you minimize the on your hand you
can see you can say that the organism
maintains its forms and function by
minimizing surprise and that is uh
maximizing model evidence
but on the other hand
if you do this
um you're gonna be able to compute the
approximate posterior that a good
approximate posterior
about the states the q and x the Q of x
so
in a sense here surprise minimization is
also a way
to compute a good posterior over the
states
all right great thanks for that
no
we'll return to this yes let's return to
it pick up here and any other questions
in next week
so thank you
see you all later
thank you